<?xml version="1.0"?>

<exercises  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Homework 4.4</title>

 <exercisegroup><introduction><p>Use systems to solve Problems 1<ndash/>3 about interest.</p></introduction>

<exercise number="1"><statement><p>Goodlife Insurance Company has $150,000 in fees from its clients to invest. They deposited part of the money into bonds that pay 6.5% annual interest and the rest into a mutual fund that pays 11.8% annual interest.<ol label="a">
	<li>Assign variables to the amount of money Goodlife deposited into each account, and write an equation about the sum of the deposits.</li>
	<li>Write expressions for the interest earned on each account after 1 year.</li>
	<li>Goodlife earned $12,930 interest in 1 year. Write an equation about that.</li>
	<li>Solve your system of equations to find out how much Goodlife invested in each account.</li></ol></p></statement>
<answer></answer></exercise>

<exercise number="2"><statement><p>Mario borrowed $30,000 from two banks to open a print shop. The first loan charges 12% annual interest, and the second charges 15% interest. Mario's annual interest payment on both loans together is $3750. How much did he borrow at each rate?<ol label="a">
	<li>Assign variables to the unknown quantities and make a table like the one in Example 1.</li>
	<li>Write two equations for the problem, one about the principals and one about the interests.</li>
	<li>Solve your system and answer the question in the problem.</li></ol></p></statement></exercise>

<exercise number="3"><statement><p>Stefan borrowed twice as much on his 7% car loan as on his 4% student loan. The annual interest on the car loan is $500 more than the interest on the student loan. How much did Stefan borrow on each loan?</p></statement>
<answer></answer></exercise>
</exercisegroup>

<exercisegroup><introduction><p>Solve Problems 4<ndash/>5 about mixtures. (No variables are needed!)</p></introduction>

<exercise number="4"><statement><p>The chemistry department has 80 students, of whom 35% are women. The physics department has 60 students, of whom 15% are women.
	<sidebyside><tabular top="major" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">
	<col width="20%"></col> <col width="20%"></col><col width="18%"></col><col width="20%"></col>             
                    <row bottom="minor">
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell>
                        <cell><p>Number of Students (<m>W</m>)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Percent Women (<m>r</m>)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Number of Women (<m>P</m>)</p></cell></row>
                    <row> 
                        <cell>Chemistry</cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell></row>
                    <row> 
                        <cell>Physics</cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell></row>
                    <row> 
                        <cell>Total</cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell></row>
                </tabular></sidebyside>
	<ol label="a">
	<li>How many chemistry students are women? How many physics students are women?</li>
	<li>How many students are there in both departments? How many of them are women?</li>
	<li>What percent of the students in chemistry and physics are women?</li></ol></p></statement></exercise>

<exercise number="5"><statement><p>Pipette, a French chemistry student, has 30 milliliters of a 50% solution of acid. She wants to reduce the strength by adding 12 milliliters of a 15% solution of the same acid.
	<sidebyside><tabular top="major" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">
	<col width="20%"></col> <col width="20%"></col><col width="20%"></col><col width="17%"></col>             
                    <row bottom="minor">
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell>
                        <cell><p>Number of Milliliters (<m>W</m>)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Percent Acid (<m>r</m>)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Amount of Acid (<m>P</m>)</p></cell></row>
                    <row> 
                        <cell>50% Solution</cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell></row>
                    <row> 
                        <cell>15% Solution</cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell></row>
                    <row> 
                        <cell>Mixture</cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell></row>
                </tabular></sidebyside></p>
    <p><ol label="a">
	<li>How much acid is in the 30 milliliters of 50% solution? How much acid is in the 12 milliliters of 15% solution?</li>
	<li>How much acid is in the mixture? How many milliliters of the mixture are there?</li>
	<li>What percent of the mixture is acid?</li>
	<li>Fill in the table with your answers to parts (a)-(c).</li></ol></p></statement>
<answer></answer></exercise>
</exercisegroup>

<exercisegroup><introduction><p>Use systems to solve Problems 6<ndash/>7 about mixtures.</p></introduction>

<exercise number="6"><statement><p>A pet store owner wants to mix a 12% saltwater solution and a 30% saltwater solution to obtain 45 liters of a 24% solution. How many liters of each ingredient does he need?<ol label="a">
	<li>Choose variables and make a table for the problem.</li>
	<li>Use your table to write two equations about the mixture.</li>
	<li>Solve your system and answer the question in the problem.</li></ol></p></statement></exercise>

<exercise number="7"><statement><p>A newspaper poll of 400 people stated that 58% were in favor of a recycling program. It also said that 50% of the men and 70% of the women polled favored the program. How many women were polled?</p></statement>
<answer></answer></exercise>
</exercisegroup>

<exercisegroup><introduction><p>Solve Problems 8<ndash/>9 about motion.</p></introduction>

<exercise number="8"><statement><p>Delbert and Francine leave Cedar Rapids at the same time and drive in opposite directions for 6 hours.<ol label="a">  
	<li><p>Choose variables for Delbert and Francine's speeds and fill in the table.  
		<sidebyside><tabular top="major" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">              
                    <row bottom="minor">
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell>
                        <cell>Rate</cell>
                        <cell>Time</cell>
                        <cell>Distance</cell></row>
                    <row><cell>Delbert</cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell></row>
                    <row><cell>Francine</cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell></row>
                    </tabular></sidebyside></p></li>
	<li>Make a sketch showing Cedar Rapids, Delbert, and Francine. Label your sketch with the distance that each traveled.</li>
	<li>Francine drove 5 miles per hour slower than Delbert. After 6 hours, they are 570 miles apart.  Write two equations about the problem.</li>
	<li>Solve your system to find Delbert's and Francine's speeds.</li></ol></p></statement></exercise>

<exercise number="9"><statement><p>Bonnie left Dallas and drove north at 40 miles per hour. Three hours later Clyde headed north form Dallas on the same road at 70 miles per hour until he caught up with Bonnie.<ol label="a"> 
	<li>Make a sketch showing Dallas, Bonnie, and Clyde.</li>  
	<li><p>Complete the table.
  <sidebyside><tabular top="major" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">              
                    <row bottom="minor">
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell>
                        <cell>Rate</cell>
                        <cell>Time</cell>
                        <cell>Distance</cell></row>
                    <row><cell>Bonnie</cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>t</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>d</m></cell></row>
                    <row><cell>Clyde</cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>\hphantom{0000}</m></cell></row>
                    </tabular></sidebyside></p></li>
	<li>Use your table to write two equations about the problem.</li>
	<li>Solve your system. How long did Bonnie drive before Clyde caught up? How far had she driven?</li></ol></p></statement>
<answer></answer></exercise>
</exercisegroup>
<exercisegroup><introduction><p>Use systems to solve Problems 10<ndash/>11.</p></introduction>

<exercise number="10"><statement><p>A yacht leaves San Diego and heads south, traveling at 25 miles per hour. Six hours later a Coast Guard cutter leaves San Diego traveling at 40 miles per hour and pursues the yacht. How long will it take the cutter to catch the yacht? How far will they have traveled?</p></statement></exercise>

<exercise number="11"><statement><p>Byron and Ada conduct sight-seeing tours of New England by bicycle. Byron leads the tour group at an average speed of 10 miles per hour, while Ada goes ahead at a speed of 12 miles per hour to prepare lunch. Ada arrives at the lunch stop 40 minutes (<m>\dfrac{2}{3}</m> of an hour) before the tour group. How far did the tour bicycle that morning?</p></statement>
<answer></answer></exercise>
</exercisegroup>

<exercisegroup><introduction><p>Solve by writing a single equation in two variables.</p></introduction>

<exercise number="12"><statement><p>In Julio's history class, the final grade is computed by adding 60% of the test average to 40% of the term paper grade. Julio's test average is 72.<ol label="a">  
	<li>Write an equation for Julio's final grade, <m>g</m>, in terms of his term paper grade, <m>t</m>.</li>
	<li>What will Julio's final grade be if he earns a grade of 65 on the term paper? What if he earns a grade of 80?</li>
	<li><p>Use the graph below to estimate what grade Julio must make on the term paper in order to earn afinal grade of 80 in the class.</p>
	<sidebyside width="60%"><!--<image source="images/hp-4-4-12.png"><description>graph</description></image>-->
    <image xml:id="hp-4-4-12">
        <description>graph of line</description>
        <latex-image>
        <!-- CDATA prevents certain LaTeX code from being interpreted as xml -->
        <![CDATA[\tikzset{%
        }
        \begin{tikzpicture} [scale=.35]
        \draw[cyan] (0,0) grid (20,20);
        \draw[black,very thick, ->, >=stealth'] (0,0)--(21.3,0) node[right]{$t$};
        \draw[black,very thick, ->, >=stealth'] (0,0)--(0,21.3) node[left, xshift=2]{$g$};
        \foreach \x [evaluate=\x as \xi using int(5*\x)] in  {5,10,15,20} {
         \draw[cyan, very thick] (\x,0) --++(0,20);
         \draw[cyan, very thick] (0,\x) --++(20,0);
         \draw[black] (\x,.15) --++(0,-.3) node[below, yshift=-2, fill=white, inner sep=1]   {$\xi$};
         \draw[black] (.15,\x) --++(-.3,0) node[left, xshift=-2, fill=white, inner sep=1]   {$\xi$};
        }
        \draw[red, very thick, ->, >=stealth'] (0,{.6*72/5})--(20,{(.6*72 +.4*100)/5});
        \end{tikzpicture}]]>
    </latex-image>
    </image>
    </sidebyside></li>
	<li>Use your equation from part (a) to verify your answer algebraically.</li></ol></p></statement></exercise>
</exercisegroup>
</exercises>



