<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<section xml:id="Expressions-and-Equations"   xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Expressions and Equations</title>

<subsection><title>Writing Algebraic Expressions</title>

<p>When we write an algebraic expression, we use the same operations on a variable that we would use to calculate with a specific number. Writing down the expression for a specific numerical value can help us write an algebraic expression.</p>

<example><statement><p>Alida keeps $100 in cash from her weekly paycheck, and deposits 40% of the remainder in her savings account. If Alida's paycheck is <m>p</m>, write an expression for the amount she deposits in savings.</p></statement>

<solution><p>How would we calculate Alida's deposit if we knew her paycheck? Suppose Alida's paycheck is $500. First she subtracts $100 from that amount to get <m>500-100</m>, and then she takes 40% of the remainder for savings:
	<me>0.40(\alert{500}-100)~~~~~\blert{\text{Perform operations inside parentheses first.}}</me>
If her paycheck is <m>p</m> dollars, we perform the same operations on <m>p</m> instead of on 500. The expression is thus
	<me>0.40(\alert{p}-100)</me></p></solution></example>

<reading-questions>
    <exercise number="1"><statement><p>We write an expression with variables using the same operations we would use to calculate with a <fillin characters="6"/>.</p></statement>
    	<answer><p>specific number</p></answer></exercise>
    <exercise number="2"><statement><p>In Example 1, how does Alida calculate the amount to deposit in savings? How do we write that in an algebraic expression?</p></statement>
    	<answer><p>Subtract 100 from her paycheck, then multiply the result by 0.40. <m>0.40(p-100)</m></p></answer></exercise>
</reading-questions>
</subsection>

<subsection><title>Evaluating Algebraic Expressions</title>
<p>When we evaluate an algebraic expression, we must follow the order of operations.</p>

<example><statement><p>Four students bought concert tickets with their $20 student-discount coupons.<ol label="a">
	<li>If the regular price of a ticket is <m>t</m> dollars, write an expression for the total amount the four students paid.</li>
	<li>How much did the students pay if the regular price of a ticket is $38?</li></ol></p></statement>
<solution><p><ol label="a">
	<li><p>The discount price of one ticket is <m>t-20</m> dollars. So four tickets cost 
		<me>4(t-20)~~\text{dollars}</me></p></li>
	<li><p>We evaluate the expression in part (a) for <m>t=38</m>.         
		\begin{align*}
               4(t-20) \amp = 4(\alert{38}-20) \amp  \blert{\text{Simplify inside parentheses first.}}\\
                \amp = 4(18)=72                
                \end{align*}					
		The students paid $72 for the tickets.</p></li></ol></p></solution></example>

<reading-questions>
    <exercise number="3"><statement><p>Explain why we need parentheses in Example 2.</p></statement>
    	<answer><p>We need to subtract before we multiply.</p></answer></exercise>
    <exercise number="4"><statement><p>How should we write "3 times the sum of <m>x</m> and 12"?</p></statement>
    	<answer><p><m>3(x+12)</m></p></answer></exercise>
</reading-questions>
</subsection>

<subsection><title>Negative Numbers</title>
<p>The order of operations applies to signed numbers. Operations inside parentheses or other grouping devices should be performed first.</p>

<example><statement><p>Simplify  <m>~~4-3-[-6+(-5)-(-2)]</m></p></statement>

<solution><p>Perform the operations inside brackets first. Simplify each step by rewriting subtractions as equivalent additions. 
	\begin{align*}
              4-3- \amp [-6+\blert{(-5)-(-2)}] \amp  \blert{-5-(-2)=-5+2}\\
                \amp = 4-3-[\blert{-6-5+2)}]    \amp \blert{-6-5=-11;~-11+2=-9}\\
                \amp = 4 \blert{-3-[-9]}        \amp \blert{\text{Rewrite as an addition.}}\\
                \amp = 4-3+9 = 10               \amp  \blert{\text{Add from left to right.}}           
                \end{align*}</p></solution></example>

<reading-questions>
    <exercise number="5"><statement><p>Which operation is performed first in the expression <m>6-4x</m>?</p></statement>
    	<answer><p>multiplication</p></answer></exercise>
    <exercise number="6"><statement><p>What is the first step in evaluating the expression <m>2(18-x)</m>?</p></statement>
    	<answer><p>Subtract <m>x</m> from 18</p></answer></exercise>
</reading-questions>

<warning><p>When using negative numbers, we must be careful to distinguish between products and sums.  In Example 4, note how the parentheses and minus signs are used in each expression.</p></warning>

<example><statement><p>Simplify each expression.<ol label="a" cols="4">
	<li><m>3(-8)</m></li>
	<li><m>3-(-8)</m></li>
	<li><m>3-8</m></li>
	<li><m>-3-8</m></li></ol></p></statement>
<solution><p><ol label="a">
	<li><p>This expression is a product: <m>~3(-8)=-24</m></p></li> 
	<li><p>This is a subtraction. We follow the rule for subtraction by changing the sign of the second number and then adding: <m>~3-(-8)=3+8=11</m></p></li> 
	<li><p>This is an addition; the negative sign in front of  tells us that we are adding <m>-8</m> to <m>3</m>. Thus, <m>~3-8=3+(-8)=-5</m></p></li> 
	<li><p>This is also an addition: <m>~-3-8=-3+(-8)=-11</m></p></li></ol></p></solution></example>

<reading-questions>
    <exercise number="7"><statement><p>What is wrong with this calculation: <m>4-3+9=4-12=-8</m>?</p></statement>
    	<answer><p>We should subtract <m>4-3</m> first.</p></answer></exercise>
</reading-questions>

<assemblage><title>Look Closer</title>
<p>When we evaluate an algebraic expression at a negative number, we enclose the negative numbers in parentheses. This will help prevent us from confusing multiplication with subtraction.</p></assemblage>

<example><statement><p>Evaluate <m>2x-3xy</m> for <m>x=-5</m> and <m>y=-2</m>.</p></statement>

<solution><p>We substitute <m>\alert{-5}</m> for <m>x</m> and <m>\blert{-2}</m> for <m>y</m>, then follow the order of operations.
	\begin{align*}
              2x-3xy \amp  2(\alert{-5})-3(\alert{-5})(\blert{-2})  \amp \blert{\text{ Do multiplications first.}}\\
                \amp = -10-(-15)(-2)\\
                \amp = -10-(-15)(-2)\\
                \amp = -10-30=-40           
                \end{align*}</p></solution></example>

<reading-questions>
    <exercise number="8"><statement><p>When we evaluate an expression at a negative number, we should <fillin characters="6"/> the negative number in <fillin characters="6"/>.</p></statement>
    	<answer><p>enclose; parentheses</p></answer></exercise>
</reading-questions>
</subsection>

<subsection><title>Skills Warm-Up</title>
<exercises>
<exercisegroup><introduction><p>Choose the correct algebraic expression for each of the following situations.
	\begin{align*}
              \amp n+12  \amp   \amp 12n    \amp  \amp \dfrac{n}{12}\\
              \amp \dfrac{12}{n} \amp \amp 12-n   \amp  \amp n-12          
                \end{align*}</p></introduction>

<exercise number="1"><statement><p>Helen bought <m>n</m> packages of tulip bulbs. If each package contains 12 bulbs, how many bulbs did she buy?</p></statement>
<answer><m>12n</m></answer></exercise>

<exercise number="2"><statement><p>Henry bought a package of <m>n</m> gladiolus bulbs, then bought 12 loose bulbs. How many bulbs did he buy?</p></statement>
<answer><m>n+12</m></answer></exercise>

<exercise number="3"><statement><p>Together Karen and Dave sold 12 tickets to the spring concert. If Karen sold <m>n</m> tickets, how many did Dave sell?</p></statement>
<answer><m>12-n</m></answer></exercise>

<exercise number="4"><statement><p>Together Karl and Diana collected <m>n</m> used books for the book sale. If Karl collected 12 books, how many did Diana collect?
</p></statement>
<answer><m>n-12</m></answer></exercise>

<exercise number="5"><statement><p>Greta made <m>n</m> dollars last week. If she worked for 12 hours, how much did she make per hour?</p></statement>
<answer><m>\dfrac{n}{12}</m></answer></exercise>

<exercise number="6"><statement><p>Gert jogged for 12 minutes. If she jogged <m>n</m> miles, how many minutes does it take her to jog 1 mile?</p></statement>
<answer><m>\dfrac{12}{n}</m></answer></exercise>
</exercisegroup>
</exercises>

</subsection>
</section>